<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reproducible workflow | Begum Topcuoglu</title>
    <link>https://begumtopcuoglu.com/tags/reproducible-workflow/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://begumtopcuoglu.com/tags/reproducible-workflow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>reproducible workflow</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://begumtopcuoglu.com/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>reproducible workflow</title>
      <link>https://begumtopcuoglu.com/tags/reproducible-workflow/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>mikropML is on CRAN!</title>
      <link>https://begumtopcuoglu.com/project/machine_learning_pipeline/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://begumtopcuoglu.com/project/machine_learning_pipeline/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning (ML) for classification and prediction based on a set of
features is used to make decisions in healthcare, economics, criminal justice
and more. However, implementing an ML pipeline including preprocessing, model
selection, and evaluation can be time-consuming, confusing, and difficult. Here,
we present &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schlosslab.org/mikropml/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mikropml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (prononced
&amp;ldquo;meek-ROPE em el&amp;rdquo;), an easy-to-use R package that implements ML pipelines using
regression, support vector machines, decision trees, random forest, or
gradient-boosted trees. The package is available on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SchlossLab/mikropml/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=mikropml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://anaconda.org/conda-forge/r-mikropml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;conda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;statement-of-need&#34;&gt;Statement of need&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most applications of machine learning (ML) require reproducible steps for data
pre-processing, cross-validation, testing, model evaluation, and often
interpretation of why the model makes particular predictions. Performing these
steps is important, as failure to implement them can result in incorrect and
misleading results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supervised ML is widely used to recognize patterns in large datasets and to make
predictions about outcomes of interest. Several packages including &lt;code&gt;caret&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;tidymodels&lt;/code&gt;  in R,
&lt;code&gt;scikitlearn&lt;/code&gt; in Python, and the H2O &lt;code&gt;autoML&lt;/code&gt;
platform allow scientists to train ML models with a variety of
algorithms. While these packages provide the tools necessary for each ML step,
they do not implement a complete ML pipeline according to good practices in the
literature. This makes it difficult for practitioners new to ML to easily begin
to perform ML analyses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable a broader range of researchers to apply ML to their problem domains,
we created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SchlossLab/mikropml/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mikropml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an easy-to-use
R package that implements the ML pipeline created by
Topçuoğlu &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2020 in a single function that returns a trained model,
model performance metrics and feature importance. &lt;code&gt;mikropml&lt;/code&gt; leverages
the &lt;code&gt;caret&lt;/code&gt; package to support several ML algorithms: linear regression,
logistic regression, support vector machines with a radial basis kernel,
decision trees, random forest, and gradient boosted trees. It incorporates good
practices in ML training, testing, and model evaluation. Furthermore, it
provides data preprocessing steps based on the FIDDLE (FlexIble Data-Driven
pipeLinE) framework outlined in Tang &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2020 and
post-training permutation importance steps to estimate the importance of each
feature in the models trained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;mikropml&lt;/code&gt; can be used as a starting point in the application of ML to datasets
from many different fields. It has already been applied to microbiome data to
categorize patients with colorectal cancer to
identify differences in genomic and clinical features associated with bacterial
infections and to predict gender-based biases in academic
publishing .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mikropml-package&#34;&gt;mikropml package&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;mikropml&lt;/code&gt; package includes functionality to preprocess the data, train ML
models, evaluate model performance, and quantify feature importance (Figure 1).
We also provide
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schlosslab.org/mikropml/articles/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;vignettes&lt;/a&gt; and an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SchlossLab/mikropml-snakemake-workflow&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;example Snakemake
workflow&lt;/a&gt; to showcase how to run an ideal ML pipeline
with multiple different train/test data splits. The results can be visualized
using helper functions that use &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mikropml allows users to get started quickly and facilitates
reproducibility, it is not a replacement for understanding the ML workflow which
is still necessary when interpreting results. To
facilitate understanding and enable one to tailor the code to their application,
we have heavily commented the code and have provided supporting documentation
which can be read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.schlosslab.org/mikropml/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank members of the Schloss Lab who participated in code clubs related to
the initial development of the pipeline, made documentation improvements, and
provided general feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;funding&#34;&gt;Funding&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salary support for PDS came from NIH grant 1R01CA215574. KLS received support
from the NIH Training Program in Bioinformatics (T32 GM070449). ZL received
support from the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship
Program under Grant No. DGE 1256260. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or
recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not
necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;author-contributions&#34;&gt;Author contributions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BDT, ZL, and KLS contributed equally. Author order among the co-first authors
was determined by time since joining the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BDT, ZL, and KLS conceptualized the study and wrote the code. KLS structured the
code in R package form. BDT, ZL, JW, and PDS developed methodology. PDS, ES, and
JW supervised the project. BDT, ZL, and KLS wrote the original draft. All
authors reviewed and edited the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
